<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An inuectyue agaynst dronkennes</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1548</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04068</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14126</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120464</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855661</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855661</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21163</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04068)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21163)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 62:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An inuectyue agaynst dronkennes</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[30] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Me Ihon Oswen],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at Ippiswiche :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1548?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A B.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon. Suggested publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Title within ornamental border.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Temperance --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21163:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21163:1"/>
            <p>❀ An in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uectyue agaynſt dron<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kennes.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Prouer. <hi>20.</hi> A</bibl>
               <p>Wyne maketh a man ſcornfull, and dronken<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes maketh a man vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quiet, he that delyteth therein, ſhall neuer be wyſe.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="epigraph">
            <pb facs="tcp:21163:2"/>
            <q>
               <bibl>Iohel. 1. A</bibl>
               <p>Awake vp you dron<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kards, wepe &amp; mourn you wyne ſuppers, be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe of youre ſweete wyne: for it ſhal be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of your mouth.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="polemic_against_drunkenness">
            <pb facs="tcp:21163:2"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> drede it mu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che leſt that ſuche as be ſobre ſholde ſcornefully deryde me for my diſcours and in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uaying agaynſt them y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> be dronken,
<note place="margin">The pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>emy.</note> as lyght and laboure loſte and tryfled tyme in vayne for they will ſaye, that ſuch caſtigacion / as to ſobre me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it nedeth not ſo vnto dronkerdes it bootethe not: whiche
<pb facs="tcp:21163:3"/>wallowynge invayne can nother heare anye mannes voyce, vnder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtande hys fryendlye admonytio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nor feleth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poygnant ſharpenes of any rebuke. For in lyke caſe, as a dead corps can w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente pryckynge, be made to feele: no more can y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mynde of a dron<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kard be ſtirred vp w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny admoniſſhements. And albeit it ware to
<pb facs="tcp:21163:3"/>be wiſſhed, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> mens la<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bour ſhuld not be loſte in chaſtenynge of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are ſo wedded to their vice &amp; wilfullnes that all hope of amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement vtterly is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, yet that not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſtandyng, for as moch as ſome there be whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che otherwhiles &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>twixt times, as it wer awaking out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> depe ſlepe of that ſo great an euy<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> them
<pb facs="tcp:21163:4"/>ſelues and declare the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues no leſſe, but to be in caſe to be holpen in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they do acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge ſome time theyr own diſeaſe: I wil eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for their ſakes, now as briefly as I can, de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clare what outrage &amp; enormitye is in thys foule vice conteyned: for as ther is nothing moore beautyfull,
<note place="margin">Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ſobre man <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſt and redy <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> hyng
<pb facs="tcp:21163:4"/>in what ſo euer tyme and place you wyll haue hym: ſo is there no monſter more hug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye then a dronkerde whoſe handes &amp; fete, as Terence ſayth, can nother of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do their dutie And fyrſt of al, I can muche prayſe the wiſedome of the Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes,
<note place="margin">The ety mologie of the woord.</note> who in the propri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>etie of theyr language do manyfeſtly expreſſe how great a vertewe
<pb facs="tcp:21163:5"/>and how exellente is ſobrietie for to thente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t they myght declare, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the mynde of man can not contynewe in hys dignytie w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out ſobri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etie, they haue called this vertue by a good ly name, <hi>SOPHROSYNE,</hi> which ſignyfyeth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng els but the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of the mynd that in how muche ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dothe excell all vnrea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſonable Creatures in
<pb facs="tcp:21163:5"/>worthyneſſe of mynde ſo muche ſhould thys vertu be eſtemed abo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue all other excellent &amp; albeit, that certayne Phyloſophers of the ſecte of zeno holde opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that he that hath one vertew, wanteth not the reſydew: yet neuertheleſſe, it is ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeene by experyence, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath had fortitude which hathe not kepte the lawes o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Almytie.
<pb facs="tcp:21163:6"/>But without the fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſobrietie, was neuer ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yet, endued w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> other vertues. For in like caſe, as that eye onely can iudge beſt the diuerſytie of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours,
<note place="margin">lyke.</note> which is cleare without any blemyſh of euil humor or other infection: ſoo can that mynd diſcerne in eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye thynge, what is to be eſc<gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>d, &amp; what is to be followed, whiche
<pb facs="tcp:21163:6"/>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> temperancie of meat and drynke, kepe the cleare from any burde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> This vnto wiſe men is mother of all good Counſels. This put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in execution, all wittie deuiſes. This maketh common wel thes to floryſhe. And with out this the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſte thynges decaye. So that euen hereof is it manyfeſte, howe great a miſchief in a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monne
<pb facs="tcp:21163:7"/>wealthe, is a dronken citeſyn,
<note place="margin">Declara<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion.</note> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che as he is cleane w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all vertue and ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſtie: ſo ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he nother in doubtfull matters gyue any counſell him ſelfe, nor followe that ſhall be gyuen hym of others, as oone that nother can remembre thynges paſte, nother vnderſtande y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which is preſent, nother fore <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee thynges to come:
<pb facs="tcp:21163:7"/>finally, who is nothing elſe, but as the Poete ſayeth of idle perſons, <hi>Telluris mutile pondus,</hi> an vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>profitable burden of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earthe. Furthermore,
<note place="margin">It fey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</note> painte in your mynde withe the Penſyll of your thought, ſuche a mannes life from eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng till it be far forth nyghtes, There is cry enge, there is dryne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng, there is playeng there is ſinginge, ther
<pb facs="tcp:21163:8"/>is talkyng of bawdry, There is hod lynge, ther is Chiding there is fighryng and braw lynge, there is brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge of pottes there is vieng &amp; vomytyng, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhame it is to heare. Then are ſome taken withe ſlepe ſo heuy as it ware euen deathe: ſome ar trubled w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites &amp; other thinges moſt terrible in theyr dremes. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> enſueth
<pb facs="tcp:21163:8"/>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iuſte punyſhment of dronke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes, great hed<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ache and debilitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> members. On y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> morow, ache and wine notte as yet digeſted, kepeth hym in bed tyl none. But &amp; if he haue any vrgente buſyneſſe to do, he goeth there a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>boute as it were a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> worne and halfe dead. And who ſhall euer do anye thynge purpoſly in a matter of weighti
<pb facs="tcp:21163:9"/>importaunce, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vntoo hee commethe with ſo euyll a wyll, ſo faynt, and weak in his lymmes? What thing can he diſpatche being hym ſelf laden? What thynge ſtrongly can a weake man do? What laboure can he endure which with drynkyng ouer nyghte, was not onelye weakened and weryed: but alſo clene ouer throwen? Muſte
<pb facs="tcp:21163:9"/>he touche any thinge? His handes haue the paulſy. Muſt he go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye whyther, his leg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges ſtacker,
<note place="margin">Compa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riſon.</note> ſo he ree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, and maketh inde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures. Doth the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter requyre eloquence Hys tonge ſtamereth, his voyce wyll not let hym ſpeake, and to be ſhorte, amongeſte all kynd of diſeſes (wher vnto the myſerable co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dytion of man is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecte,
<pb facs="tcp:21163:10"/>there is none at all to be found, that ſo whollye take the man from all vſe of him ſelf and ouerthrowethe both body and mynde as dothe thys vyce of dronkennes. For al o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſeſes, what tim they do aſſayle the bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy or any parte therof yet dare they not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempte, to pearce the mind, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> immortal part of man.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21163:10"/>
            <p> For ſom haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cra<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> and ſome the goute, ſome hote diſeſes and ſome colde: yet haue they ſtyh the vſe of re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon in her chief perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſelfe ſame thyng which we haue common and all <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>one wyth God, wherbye, both we are, and ſo be ryghtlye called, men<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wherin <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, we differ from brute beſtes, dro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kennes bothe can and
<pb facs="tcp:21163:11"/>is alſo accuſtomablye wonte to confounde &amp; bring to naught.
<note place="margin">Falling ſycknes</note> The fallyng ſycknes is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly a cruel and a dreadefull dyſeaſe, wherin many ar wont often times to deſtroy them ſelues, whyleſte they beate their owne membres, teare theyr heyre, and wallow the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> myre. But no man is able wythe woordes to expreſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:21163:11"/>how much more beaſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly and deteſtable, dron<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kennes is: for whom ſo euer the fallyng ſick<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes taketh, it leaueth hym by and by, and re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtoreth vnto hym the vſe of his mind again. But the dronkerd af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that he hath longe &amp; much bene tormoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with dronkenſhip, and hath both done &amp; ſuffred many thynges full ſhamefully (vnles
<pb facs="tcp:21163:12"/>he ware by and by as often tymes it chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth vtterly extinguiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhed therein) and hath leyne two or thre dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es lyke a deade man, ſcarſly then commeth agayn to himſelf. The other mannes diſeaſe is leſſe euyll for thys cauſe, that nothynge is committed through his fault, but through the vehemencie of his diſeaſe. He repenteth
<pb facs="tcp:21163:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>that he hath ſayd and done: but thys manne hath a double euyll, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he can laye the blame vpon none other, and that ſuche thynges do more greue me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which chaunce vnto them w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out deſerte. Agayn, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſte the diſeaſes of the mynde, there is none ſo hurtfull,
<note place="margin">Thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed.</note> nor where vpon groweth and enſueth ſo muche wickednes to be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d.
<pb facs="tcp:21163:13"/>For once, what thyng is ſo abhomynable y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> dronkerdes dare not doo?
<note place="margin">Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentes</note> Nothyng ought amongeſte men to be more reuerentli obſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued, then faythe and counſell keapyng: but thou mayſt commytte nothing in creadite to a dronckarde: for he bloweth it abrode and can kepe no counſel, be it neuer ſo reuerent a thynge, neuer ſo holy,
<pb facs="tcp:21163:13"/>neuer ſo much nede to be kepte ſecrete, but if he be prouoked vnto ſuch folly by any dron<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken companion of his,
<note place="margin">The cauſe.</note> he bewrayeth and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayeth the high dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of his mynde: for what thinge is it that he wyll not dyſclooſe which is ſo ready and ſo greadye at the foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſſhe requeſte and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of oothers, to loſe that thynge that
<pb facs="tcp:21163:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>he hath in this world deereſt.
<note place="margin">Effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.</note> And to whom is it vnknowen that dronkennes is an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerflowyng founteyn and welſprynge of all myſchiefes, of conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſtrife and debate, woundyng of men, ra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uyſſhynge of women, murdre &amp; aduoutry. It is euydently kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen, that the greate fyght of the Lapithes (as Horace makethe
<pb facs="tcp:21163:14"/>mention) aroſe onelye vpon wyne, &amp; we now at this dai haue to ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny examples thereof: and dyd not Tharqui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nius kyng of Romai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, after that he had in his cuppes, goo and rauyſhe that good wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>man Lucrece, and loſt therby his kyngdom? Who knoweth not, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> great Alexander king of Macedonia, in al o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thynges a prince
<pb facs="tcp:21163:15"/>moſte excellente and a famous conquerer, in his dronkennes wold ſley his moſte deare &amp; famyliar frendes, and ſo loſte the loue of hys Lordes therby, that in fyne, he was poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned.
<note place="margin">A briefe perora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> But men maye impute to me greate folly, which go aboute wythe the ſhortneſſe of ſpeache to compriſe anne endleſſe matter, whoſe myſchief ſtret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth
<pb facs="tcp:21163:15"/>ſo farre, that in caſe I had an hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred wittes with as many tongues, &amp; a mouth of braſſe or yron, yet ware I no thynge able to vtter the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyls that ariſe of dronken<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:21163:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Imprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at Ippiſwiche by me Ihon Oſwen.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="license">
            <p>Cum priuilegio ad Imprimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum ſolum.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21163:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
